Finding Aid for William Warner Bishop papers, 1928-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Warner Bishop papers
1928-1987
Bishop, William Warner, 1906-
85113 Aa 2
Professor of international law at the University of Michigan. Correspondence and other files relating to his professional and academic activities, including work with the American Bar Association Section of International and Comparative Law, the American Society of International Law, the International Law Association, and the Committee on International and Comparative Law of the State Bar of Michigan.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Professor Bishop, and after his death by his daughter, Elizabeth S. Bishop (donor no. 6173 ). The collection came in various accessions beginning in 1978.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
William Warner Bishop, Jr. was born in Princeton, New Jersey, on June 10, 1906, the son of William Warner Bishop (1871-1955), who later became librarian of the University of Michigan, and Finnie Murfree (Burton) Bishop. He received his Bachelor of Arts from the University of Michigan in 1928, spent one year on post-graduate work at Harvard, and received his Doctor of Jurisprudence from the University of Michigan in 1931. He was admitted to the Michigan Bar later that same year.
Bishop worked as a research and teaching assistant at the University of Michigan Law School from 1931 to 1935. He was an assistant reporter for the Harvard Research on International Law from 1932 to 1935. In 1935-36 he was with the New York law firm of Root, Clarke, Butler, and Ballentine. From 1936 to 1938, he lectured on politics at Princeton. In 1939, Bishop became an assistant legal advisor for the U.S. Department of State. He remained at that post until 1947 when he accepted a position at the Law School of the University of Pennsylvania as a visiting professor of international law. Bishop accepted a position as professor of international law at the University of Michigan in 1948, a position he held until 1976.
Throughout his career, Bishop held different positions concerned with international law. He was legal adviser to the United States delegation to the Council of Foreign Ministers at the Paris Peace Conference in 1946. In 1961 and again in 1965, he was a guest lecturer at the Hague Academy of International Law; and from 1975 to 1981, he was a member of the Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague.
An active member of law associations and editorial boards of journals, Bishop was vice-president of the American Society of International Law (1960-1961), honorary vice-president (1969-1982 and 1984-1987), and honorary president (1982-1984). From 1953 to 1955 and from 1962 to 1970 Bishop was editor-in-chief of the American Journal of International Law. Bishop was also co-director of International Legal Studies at the University of Michigan Law School from 1958 to 1976. He held the University of Michigan's Distinguished Professorship Award from 1966 to 1976. In 1977, Bishop was named professor emeritus. Bishop authored the leading law school casebook on international law from the 1950s through the 1970s, International Law Cases and Materials.
On July 19, 1947, Bishop married Mary Fairfax Shreve (died November 18, 1979). They had one daughter, Elizabeth Shreve Bishop. Bishop died December 29, 1987.
The papers of William Warner Bishop, Jr., covering the period from 1928 to 1987, consist of six linear feet of correspondence, course materials, addresses and professional papers. The collection has been arranged into six series: Biographical/Personal; Addresses, Papers, etc.; Associations; Professional Correspondence; and Course Materials. The collection relates mainly to Bishop's study and teaching of international law. Among the more personal files are materials relating to Bishop's lifelong activity with the local area Boy Scouts.
Subjects:
American Bar Association.; American Society of International Law.; Atlantic Union (U.S.); International law.; International Law Association.; Law.; State Bar of Michigan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.Law School.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bishop, William W. (William Warner), 1906-1987; Legal education.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
International Movement for Atlantic Union.; Merillat, H. C. L. (Herbert Christian Laing), 1915-; Vallance, William Roy, 1887-1967.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographical material (include family members) (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, memorials, tributes (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Bishop, William Warner, Sr. (letters from), 1945-1951 (Box 1)
    - Bishop family Christmas letters, 1954-1987 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous family letters (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Boy Scout activities, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan football ("An all-time Michigan football team") (Box 1)
  - Writings, reviews, etc. (Box 1)
- Addresses, papers, etc. (arranged alphabetically by title or topic)
  - Antarctic Treaty statement, circa 1959 (Box 1)
  - Bilder/Bishop casebook revision, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Can Communist China and Iceland Extend Unilaterally Their Territorial Waters to Twelve Miles?, October 1958 (Box 1)
  - Coastal States' Jurisdiction over Foreign Merchant and Naval Vessel in its Territorial Sea and Contiguous Zone, including the Airspace Above, March 1973 (Box 1)
  - Concessions and Latin America (paper done while a graduate student at Columbia Law School), circa 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Conflict of Treaties and National Law in the United States of America (with Eric Stein), undated (Box 1)
  - Current Trends in International Law, April 1958 (Box 1)
  - A Decade of International Legal Studies at the University of Michigan Law School, 1955-1964; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Divorce in the Conflict of Laws, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Exercise of Jurisdiction for Special Purposes in High Sea Areas Beyond the Outer Limit of Territorial Waters, May 1949 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Affairs for Everyone, September 1961 (Box 1)
  - High Sea Resources, May 1967 (Box 1)
  - International and Comparative Law at Michigan after World War II and the Ford Foundation Grants, 1970 (Box 1)
  - International Control of Pollution, April 1972 (Box 1)
  - International Law in American Schools Today, 1953 (Box 1)
  - International Law, 1906-1981 (Box 1)
  - International Law of the Sea conferences, 1973-1980 (Box 1)
  - International Law Problems of Acquisition and Transportation of Antarctic Icebergs, 1977 (Box 1)
  - International Relations of Haiti and the United States Since the Year 1900 - Thesis, January 1928 (Box 1)
  - International Rule of Law, June 1960 (Box 1)
  - Introduction to International Law State Responsibility to Aliens, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Law of Nations, undated (Box 1)
  - Legal Aspects of the International Protection of Human Rights, December 1968 (Box 1)
  - Objectives of International Law Courses in Law Schools, August 1948 (Box 1)
  - Peace Treaties of World War II (Box 1)
  - Perpetual Treaties, February 1961 (Box 1)
  - Progressive Development of International Law, December 1947 (Box 1)
  - Refugees, January 1981 (Box 1)
  - Responsibilities of States, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Role of International Law in a Peaceful World Order, March 1984 (Box 1)
  - Scope and Method of International Law Courses, an Introduction, July 1954 (Box 1)
  - Situation of Buick Navidzadeh, December 1954 (Box 1)
  - Supplementary Materials on International Law (to be used with E.D. Dickinson's Cases on the Law of Nations at the University of Michigan, 1933-1935) (Box 1)
  - Treaties, October 1965 (Box 1)
  - Vietnam Legal Aspects, February 1966 (Box 1)
  - What is International Law and what is it good for?, September 1959 (Box 1)
  - World Affairs, March 1963 (Box 1)
- Associations
  - American Bar Association, Section of International and Comparative Law, October 1948-December 1953
    - Committee on Fisheries and Territorial Waters, April 1947-January 1964 (Box 1)
    - Committee on International Law in the Courts of the United States, November 1954-November 1963 (Box 1)
    - Committee on the Teaching of International and Comparative Law, February 1947-March 1956 (Box 1)
  - American Journal of Comparative Law, April-November 1967 (Box 1)
  - American Journal of International Law
    - Baxter, Dick, April 1966-December 1975 (Box 1)
    - Briggs, Herbert, April 1962-December 1968 (Box 1)
    - Dillard, Hardy, May 1963-July 1968 (Box 1)
    - Editor's Choice, February-April 1962 (Box 1)
    - Editor's Files, January 1954-March 1968 (Box 1)
    - Evans, Alona, November 1966-February 1976 (Box 2)
    - Finch, Eleanor, 1963; 1967-January 1972; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Fenwick, Charles, November 1963-May 1972 (Box 2)
    - Freeman, Al, September 1963-April 1984 (Box 2)
    - Gross, Leo, October 1965-September 1972 (Box 2)
    - Hazard, John, May 1962-1969 (Box 2)
    - International Court of Justice, March 1969 (Box 2)
    - Jessup, Philip, June 1963-November 1969 (Box 2)
    - Metzger, Stanley, May 1964-March 1967 (Box 2)
    - Schachter, Oscar, April 1962-February 1972 (Box 2)
    - Sohn, Louis, September 1964-May 1967 (Box 2)
    - Stevenson, John, September 1962-January 1967 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, April 1962-February 1977 (Box 2)
  - American Society of International Law
    - H.C.L. Merillat, vice-president and executive director
      - June 1961-April 1967 (Box 2)
      - Re: regulations, April 1961 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, July 1960-September 1983 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, April 1972-November 1973 (Box 2)
    - Panel on State Responsibility, March 1972-April 1979 (Box 2)
    - Volume on State Responsibility, May-December 1975 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Law Schools (re: Institute plans), May 1947-November 1950 (Box 2)
  - Inter-American Bar, June 1948-March 1964 (Box 2)
  - International Law Association
    - Committee on State Immunity, March 1953-May 1964 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, May 1947-April 1968 (Box 2)
  - State Bar of Michigan
    - Committee on Cooperation with the Inter-American Bar Association, November 1949-February 1959 (Box 2)
    - Committee on International and Comparative Law, November 1953-November 1967 (Box 2)
- Professional correspondence
  - Allen, Edward, October 1954-November 1976 (Box 2)
  - Black Action Movement (BAM), March 1970 (Box 2)
  - Bernini, Giorgio, November 1967-April 1982 (Box 2)
  - Bevans, Charles, March 1948-January 1975 (Box 2)
  - Brussels (Free University of), September 1972-June 1977 (Box 2)
  - Campbell Competition case, March 1959-April 1966 (Box 2)
  - Christiansen, James, October 1953-June 1973 (Box 2)
  - Columbia University, November 1947-July 1948 (Box 2)
  - Dickinson, Edwin D., July 1933-April 1970 (Box 2)
  - Dorsey, Gary, 1950-September 1962 (Box 2)
  - English, Ben, November 1950-June 1959 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Exchange Bulletin, May-June 1963 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Relations Advisory Committee, September 1965-March 1968 (Box 2)
  - Franklin, William, September 1963-November 1965 (Box 2)
  - Freeman, Al, July 1947-December 1972 (Box 3)
  - Friedmann, Wolfgang, November 1965-March 1967 (Box 3)
  - Garretson, A.H., February 1947-November 1975 (Box 3)
  - George, B.J., June 1957-September 1963 (Box 3)
  - Goldman, Ernest, November 1955-November 1963 (Box 3)
  - Gomes, Mary, February 1965-June 1987 (Box 3)
  - Gould, Wesley, October 1956-April 1960 (Box 3)
  - Griffin, William, July 1949-June 1972 (Box 3)
  - Hague Academy, 1960-February 1977 (Box 3)
  - Harrison, E.G., February 1948-November 1950 (Box 3)
  - Harvard Research, 1949-1958 (Box 3)
  - Instit de Droit International (Gilbert Gidel), July 1952-February 1973 (Box 3)
  - International Movement for Atlantic Union (Mrs. Chase S. Osborn, secretary), April 1960-October 1968 (Box 3)
  - Iranian claims, November 1983-May 1984 (Box 3)
  - Istanbul (includes lectures), October 1957-September 1958 (Box 3)
  - Jackson, John, 1966-January 1985 (Box 3)
  - Jessup, Philip, June 1942-April 1981 (Box 3)
  - Judge Advocate General's School, July 1963-August 1966 (Box 3)
  - Johnson, Ralph, November 1960-February 1967 (Box 3)
  - Johnston, D.M., July-October 1963 (Box 3)
  - Kerno, Ivan, March-May 1953 (Box 3)
  - Klooz, Marie, June 1952-February 1964 (Box 3)
  - Knauth, Arnold, May 1948-April 1960 (Box 3)
  - Lee, Luke, November 1955-April 1982 (Box 3)
  - Leonard, L., December 1953-January 1966 (Box 3)
  - Leyser, Johannes, February 1964-September 1967 (Box 3)
  - Lissitzyn, Oliver, February 1949-1958 (Box 3)
  - MacChesney, Brunson, February 1950-March 1964 (Box 3)
  - McDougal, Myres, June 1950-October 1986 (Box 3)
  - Meader, George, February 1951-May 1959 (Box 3)
  - Michigan, University of, Faculty Advisory Committee on International Programs, minutes, January-March 1968 (Box 3)
  - Michigan, University, Teaching Methods Committee, March-May 1952 (Box 3)
  - Morocco, December 1947-June 1949 (Box 3)
  - Nadelmann, Kurt, November 1948-February 1978 (Box 3)
  - Newhouse, Wade, October 1953-August 1979 (Box 3)
  - New Jersey Industries, Inc., May 1951 (Box 3)
  - Oliver, Covey, July 1949-October 1956 (Box 3)
  - Princeton, July 1936-October 1937 (Box 3)
  - Randolph, Bessie, February-March 1954 (Box 3)
  - Re, Edward, 1952-October 1965 (Box 3)
  - Reese, Willis, October-November 1962 (Box 3)
  - Regirer, Walter, June-August 1972 (Box 3)
  - Reiff, Henry, November 1953-January 1965 (Box 3)
  - Rhynem Charles, September 1959-November 1965 (Box 3)
  - Rice, William, February 1950-November 1962 (Box 3)
  - Rome Convention, December 1964-August 1965 (Box 3)
  - Seidl-Hohenveldern, Ignez, August 1950-1965 (Box 3)
  - Smith, Allan F., April 1959-June 1965 (Box 3)
  - Sohn, Louis, September 1954-January 1960 (Box 3)
  - Southern Methodist University (Joseph Norton), October 1983-March 1984 (Box 3)
  - Stanger, Ro, February 1957-November 1958 (Box 3)
  - Stason, E. Blythe, July 1951-September 1973 (Box 3)
  - State Department
    - General, 1949-February 1977 (Box 3)
    - Tate, Jack, July 1949-October 1954 (Box 3)
  - Stein, Eric, June 1958-May 1983 (Box 3)
  - Summers, Lionel, May 1949-January 1974 (Box 3)
  - Texas-Attorney General's Office, 1949-November 1950 (Box 3)
  - Texas (state), May 1950-September 1958 (Box 3)
  - Texas, University of, November 1951-1953 (Box 3)
  - Toledo, University of, October 1972-May 1980 (Box 3)
  - Vallance, William, March 1949-April 1966 (Box 3)
  - War Claims Commission, 1950-April 1953 (Box 3)
  - Wilson, Robert, November 1950-October 1966 (Box 3)
  - Whiteman, Marjorie, December 1950-1966 (Box 3)
  - Woodard, Charles, February 1953-March 1964 (Box 3)
- Course Materials (taken and taught)
  - Princeton University
    - Comparative Law lecture notes, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
    - Military Science 201 lectures, 1936-1938; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Military Science 302 lectures, 1938 (Box 3)
    - Nationality lectures, 1936 (Box 3)
    - Politics 302 lectures, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Politics 403 lectures, 1936-1938 (Box 3)
    - State Succession lecture, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Territory lectures, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Treaties lecture, 1936 (Box 3)
    - War lectures, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
  - Columbia Law School, 1938-1939
    - General (Box 4)
    - Llewellyn's Law in Society-Sales lectures (student notes and papers), February-May 1939 (Box 4)
  - University of Pennsylvania
    - Conflict of Laws lectures, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
    - International Law
      - General lectures, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
      - State Responsibility lectures, 1947 (Box 4)
      - Treaties lectures, 1947 (Box 4)
      - War Crimes lectures, 1947 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan
    - Classes taken
      - Reeves (Jesse) class in international law, 1927-1928 (Box 4)
      - Dickinson's law lectures (WWB's student notes), 1930-1932 (Box 4)
    - Classes taught
      - Admiralty, 1950-1974; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Conflict of Laws, 1948-1975; 8 folders (Box 4)
      - Conservation 293 and 490, 1950-1963 (Box 4)
      - Curriculum Studies, 1960; 1968; 1972 (Box 4)
      - International Law (by date), circa 1932-1933; 1948-1955; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - International Law (by date), 1956-1984; 8 folders (Box 5)
      - International Law (by topic)
        - Antarctica, 1959-1967 (Box 5)
        - Banco National, 1971-1977 (Box 5)
        - Chamizal, 1963 (Box 5)
        - Civil Strife, 1971-1975 (Box 5)
        - Corporations, undated (Box 5)
        - Eichmann, Adolph, 1973 (Box 5)
        - European International Organizations, 1959 (Box 5)
        - Extradition, 1959-1962 (Box 5)
        - Formosa, 1958 (Box 5)
        - Hijacking, 1973 (Box 5)
        - Human Rights, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
        - Icebergs, 1977 (Box 5)
        - International Judicial Cooperation in Criminal Matters, 1962 (Box 5)
        - International Law of the Sea, 1970-1984 (Box 5)
        - International Monetary Fund, 1967 (Box 5)
        - International Problems of Criminal Law, 1950-1975; 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Introduction, 1950-1967 (Box 5)
        - Legal Education Seminar, 1964 (Box 5)
        - Nuclear Weapons Ban, 1963 (Box 5)
        - Problems (compilation of problems for class), 1966-1967 (Box 5)
        - Recognition, 1952-1983 (Box 5)
        - Reservations to Multilateral Treaties, 1961 (Box 5)
        - Resolutions, 1972 (Box 5)
        - Sabbatino, 1962-1966 (Box 5)
        - Settlement of Disputes of Treaties of Peace, undated (Box 5)
        - Space, 1971-1973 (Box 5)
        - Territorial Waters, 1982 (Box 5)
        - Theory, 1937 (Box 5)
        - Treaty Problems, 1949 (Box 5)
        - Treaties and Law of the Sea, 1978-1986 (Box 5)
        - Treaties of Commerce, Navigation, and Consular Rights, 1949-1959 (Box 5)
        - United States-Ecuador Tuna Controversy, 1971 (Box 6)
        - Vietnam, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
        - War Crimes, 1955-1975 (Box 6)
      - Political Science 464, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Law School miscellanea (regarding foreign law students, circa 1958, 1971 and curriculum development, circa 1950, 1968) (Box 6)
  - Hague Academy Lecture notes (arranged by chapter), 1965; 15 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous course notes, etc., 10 folders (Box 6)